Inventory of the Robert Saunders Letters 1829-1867
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- (9)
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 3 May 1863 (9)
    Happily hears of Lucy's recovery from Mr. James Semple. Paid broker $105 for $21 in gold to purchase article for Lucy. Semple hired out his slave, Jim, in Danville. Jim had run away once and was with the Yankees. Glad Jim has not the chance to tell other slaves of his escape. Heard nothing of slaves Molly and Elia. All their servants in Williamsburg, except Sam, who was hired at the lunatic asylum, are still in place. All slaves at the farm, except Jacob, are still there. Jacob enticed away by his wife a servant of Mrs. Tucker. All Mrs. Tuckers' slaves have run off. Thinks Yankees will abandon the lunatic asylum. If so, Lee would make some arrangements for its support. A battle is near at Fredericksburg (Chancellorsville). Funeral tomorrow, at St. Paul's, for Channing Price, killed near Fredericksburg. Does not repine or brood over his affairs. Would need only to see Lucy the children and grandchildren to be happy as anyone could be during the war. The war enrages rather than depresses him. Strongly angered, filling him with desire to see the Yankee race exterminated. Will attempt to get a promoted position when the members of Congress are gone. Believes it will be easier to approach Secretaries at that time.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 31 May 1863 (9)
    Suffering with acute diarrhea. Misses Lucy terribly. Spent an evening with General (Richard Stoddart) Ewell. Ewell 's been promoted to Lieutenant General a day or two after being married to Mrs. Brown. Ewell has gone to join General Lee's army and take command of Gen Jackson's old command. Mr. Botts lost his slaves.
- (10)
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 7 June 1863 (10)
    Recovered from diarrhea, but many of acquaintances still ill. Has not heard from Bob. Has seen Mr. Semple who offered regards to the family. There is nothing new from Williamsburg.
    Has seen Mr. Jonas, Mr. Penick, Henry and John Dix. Has not been able to get shoes the girls asked for but the importation of blockade goods is expected during the present week.
    Rumors from Vicksburg are not good news. Has seen a dispatch from General Johnston, but the information it contains cannot fully be authenticated.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 12 June 1863 (10)
    Sending unbleached cotton on Tuesday. Mr. Custis daughters had seen Lucy and Page. Sent the shoes they asked for. Has not heard from Bob. Miss Judith Carter Nelson says all servants from Shelby are gone had gone except the carriage driver and wife. Has not seen Lizzie Ewell. Has seen I. Custis and Mrs. Miles Selden.
    Yankee commander has given Dr. Garrett permission to return home.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 25 June 1863 (10)
    Accepted a position as quartermaster of the Pittsylvania District and will be relocated to Danville. Will stop at Pittsylvania on his way to Danville. Was offered a higher paying position but turned it down to be able to go to Danville and be close to the family. Eventually he will hold the rank of captain and that will reward him with a higher salary. Then he can buy from the commissary sugar, bacon, flour, salt, etc and this not for myself, but for my family. at government prices.
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 28 June 1863 (10)
    Preparing to leave Richmond to assume duties in the Quartermaster Corps collecting the tax in kind. Believes new position will be anything but sedentary, but rather laborious and require a great deal travel. for a month Feels ready for the task. Happy she received bundle and Mr. Wilmer liked the shirts. Sends regards to Miss Lizzie who he hopes to see again soon. Will try and get things Lucy requested, but he believes the blankets and the iron things will be difficult to procure. Has not heard from his daughters and hopes to before he leaves Richmond. Will not be able to go to Lexington, because he will be too busy organizing a new business not only to (him) but to the whole corps of quartermasters in the same service." Expresses regards for his grandchildren Anne and Mary. Hopes to see them at the Rectory before they leave, and to Georgy, Breck who he'll bring a spelling book a piece and candy for darling Lucy Page. Unable to see Lizzie Ewell or Colonel and Mrs. Munford.
  - Robert Saunders at the Rectory to his wife Lucy, 12 July 1863 (10)
    Salutation to My beloved wife. Send subsequent letters to Danville. Wants to hear from Bob. General Pendleton has not been injured. Mrs. Gilmer lost brother, Col. Henry Carrington, Col. Rawley Martin is wounded and a prisoner, Col. Whittle and James Poindexter are wounded again, Col. Tazewell Patton reportedly killed or wounded.
  - Robert Saunders at Danville to his wife Lucy, 30 July 1863 (10)
    Setting up districts in Pittsylvania County for the administration of the collection of the tax in kind. Has no clerk. Offered the position of county agent to Mr. Gilmer, but he declined. Then offered it to Mr. Johnson. Will travel, go to Franklin and Bedford Counties next week to organize them Lucy is to direct her next letter to Bedford County, in care of Captain Charles Mallory. News of Pittsylvania Court House relatives and friends at Pittsylvania Court. Colonel Carrington wounded in the hand and captured, Colonel Martin is assumed dead, and Captain James Poindexter and Lt. Hutchins captured. Colonel Whittle wounded but not taken prisoner, Col. Whittle and Col. Patton, wounded and imprisoned. The Poindexter and Carter boys are at home and slightly wounded.
    All are well at the Rectory, darling Lucy Page as sweet as ever. News of Williamsburg in a letter from Mr. Sydney Smith. Mr. Sweeney told him their servants were still all in place & contented. Old Mr. Pettitt has died according to Dr. Wise.
- (11)
  - Robert Saunders at Rectory to his wife Lucy, 3 August 1863 (11)
    Discusses travel plans. Very busy and doesn't have time to write. Suggests that several routes from Lexington to Danville and asks that she inform him of her travel plans. Concerned the Bob must get some certificate from Gen(eral) Smith to keep with him until he gets back to Lexington, to avoid possible delay by enrolling officers. Asks that Lucy not spend any time with Lizzie Nelson who has come all the way from the South and wants her full attention adding Circumstances force one to be selfish. My mind is as strained as have ever had it, and I cannot support an additional burden. Reports the death of Colonel Tazewell, the brother of Mrs. John Gilmer and has heard nothing about members of Lucy's family.
  - Robert Saunders at Liberty, Bedford to his wife Lucy, 7 August 1863 (11)
    Happy that she will go to Botetourt and will be comfortable there. Will be traveling all month. Sent her a check for $100 and hopes she has received it. Lelia wrote of the death of poor Mrs. Munford. He has written to Bob. Details recent travels and is now staying in Liberty for two or three days with Captain Mallory. Intends to go to Wytheville when he leaves Liberty, if the Yankees are not about, and then to Carroll, Franklin, Henry and Patrick counties. Will try to meet Bob at the Rectory. Asks that she direct her letters to Danville. Includes a biographical note stating that Captain Mallory, the brother of Dr. Mallory, is from Hampton.
  - Robert Saunders at Henry Court House to his wife Lucy, 7 September 1863 (11)
    Sent a passport to Mr. Wilmer. Hopes he has received it. Rode from Danville to Henry Court House by stage. Stayed in a fine large room in an old fashioned tavern built of logs. Is comfortable there as opposed to not being so in his other travels. Dined with an attorney Mr. Wootten, an old student at the college, and acquaintance. Wootten helping him with his business. Will resume his travels to Patrick and Franklin Counties before returning to Danville. Hopes to be reunited with Lucy before the end of next week. Has, happily, seen Mrs. Neel and Miss J. Bucktrout, daughters of Mrs. I. Bucktrout from Williamsburg. Spoke to Rev. William Lee and he is well.
  - Robert Saunders at Henry Court House to his wife Lucy, 11 September 1863 (11)
    Finding it difficult traveling from Henry Court House to Patrick Court House. There are no horses to be hiredand there is no public conveyance to Patrick Court House from any point on the globe." Travel has generally agreed with him and he is entirely well. Not suffering from gout and neuralgia he has endured in previous years at this time of the season.
  - Robert Saunders at Pittsylvania Court House to his daughter Lucy Page, 4 November 1863 (11)
    Lucy Page at the home of Mrs. Michie in Staunton. She has a beaux there, a Dr. Rush. Considers him an entirely respectable young man at his position & and has the reputation of being a very worthy one. Has traveled more than 1000 miles from end of July to 26 September. Has used more than 200 stamps on letters relating to official business. Regrets not having written her but uses the large amount of official correspondence as an excuse for not having the time to do so. Has a fond remembrance of Mrs. Jones, the former Miss Nanny Marshall. Asks to be remembered to Capt. Bagby although he is not sure that that is his name, but is sure he knows him.
- (12)
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy, 17 March 1864 (12)
    Is as busy in Richmond as he was previously.
    Disappointed to hear that Colonel Rawley Martin was not among the exchange prisoners. Bob has asked for information on how to join the army.
    Richmond at this time is very disagreeable and every thing is awfully high & things to eat are scarce. He manages, thanks to his friends. Mr. James Lyon's house in Richmond has burned to the ground.
- (13)
  - Robert Saunders at Richmond to his wife Lucy at Pittsylvania Court House, 7 March 1865 (13)
    Bob's division is expected to be ordered to Gordonsville. Hopes to see him before he leaves. Major Baker P. indicates that Bob is well and that Pickett's Division, was to be reviewed by General Lee. Colonel Benjamin S. Ewell, has been by to see him. Expects to join Lucy on Saturday, but travel is uncertain.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy, 27 July 1865 (13)
    Informs Lucy that he is well at the home of Charles Waller in Williamsburg. Traveled from Danville to Richmond, stayed with Mr. Sweeney, then to Williamsburg. The Waller invitation to lodging was one of many invitations he received. Has seen many friends and they are well. Has many things on his mind and cannot express them in a hastily written letter. Saunders Expresses his love for his wife, children and grandchildren and old friends and writes servants very kind.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Pittsylvania Court House, 13 August 1865 (13)
    Gilmer for free. Grateful to him as he didn't have the money to pay for it. Sent the application, along with the regular applications for pardon, to Washington, by way of Richmond where it was signed with a recommendation for acceptance by Governor Pierpont. Received his property in town without difficulty, but is concerned about York County land holdings. Anxious that the pardon be accepted and for the complete restoration of property. Suspects he will have to go to Washington to see to the matter.
    Of Williamsburg he writes there is nothing doing here, nor is there any prospect, for some time at least for any one to do any thing in any department of human employment to support himself. Everything is disjointed and in a languishing condition and he would not return to Williamsburg this year if he could get something to do which would barely support life in Pittsylvania or elsewhere for the next year. The families of Colonel Munford, Dr. Mercer and Dr. Canius (?). are the only one's to return to Williamsburg.
    Envelope addressed to Lucy, care of Mr. J. Clarke, Esq. Danville attached.
  - Robert Saunders at Washington to his wife Lucy, 27 August 1865 (13)
    Had dinner with Peggy and her husband, William Botts in Richmond. They and their grandchildren are well. Botts has given him a letter to the President, which he delivered without being able to say much. Will attempt an interview, but is not hopeful it will occur tomorrow and he may be in Washington a few days before it occurs. Is as active as a steam printing press and shall not relax (his) efforts until (he ) succeeds in getting (his) property restored or come to a dead halt. Confident it will be restored.
- (14)
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his daughter Lucy Page at Pittsylvania Court House, 19 August 1867 (14)
    Happy she survived the disagreeable circumstances attending the unusually uncomfortable journey from Richmond to Pittsylvania Court. House. She is with Miss Sallie and is staying with Miss Mary away from the ennui of Williamsburg.Sends regards to Mr. Whittle and Mr. D. Coles. Judge and Mrs. Gilmer. Indicates great affection for his friends at Pittsylvania Court House.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy, 4 September 1867 (14)
    Secured the breast pin Lucy had forgotten.Met Col.Ewell and thanked him for his kindness as to the carriage.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his daughter, Roberta Page, 11 September 1867 (14)
    Encloses $5. Mother leaving for Mr. Botts after arriving at Richmond. Informs her that she, the Munfords, Custises and Sherwells are all well. Prof. Taliaferro and John Henley have died. Charles Wallers baby died. Prof. Millington a grand old man who is dying gradually.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Richmond, 11 September 1867 (14)
    Bob came down from Richmond by steamboat and got a chill. Administered quinine. Sending the $5 to Roberta Page. Mr. Keatts, the shoemaker, of Pittsylvania Court House came to visit. She is at Richmond with granddaughter. Williamsburg is improved in health. Their immediate friends the Mumfords, Custises and Sherwells are well. Mrs. Maupin has is at the College Hotel. and Mr. Darlington from York County is renting her house.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy at Pittsylvania Court House, 16 September 1867 (14)
    Apparently she is at Pittsylvania with Lucy Page,Peggy.Tells of Bobs chills.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his daughter Roberta Page, 25 September 1867 (14)
    Bob returned to Williamsburg with a chill and fever which was treated with quinine and other pills. Will stay with the Pettitts for a couple of days. Pleased that Lucy is in pleasant places,away from the labor of keeping house at a time when labor is to take the places of means,and when there are no servants to depend upon. The unhealthfulness of this region, including the town exceeds anything that I have ever known. Chills and fever epidemic in Williamsburg. Asks her not to come back too soon.
  - Robert Saunders at Williamsburg to his wife Lucy, 30 September 1867 (14)
    Mrs Vest has died suddenly Very sad over it. Mentions her exuberant spirit, resilient frame and defiance of misfortune. Robert Taylor,steward of the Lunatic asylum and son in law of Mrs Pettis,also has died.Confined to the house with gout.Being treated by Dr. Carmen.Has not been able to prepare the house for Lucys return even though Bob is helping.How much it will cost to bring her back from Richmond.Happy to learn that Dr. Millington is doing better. Expresses good wishes and sentiments,love for his old friend. Conveys great gratitude to Mr. and Mrs. Blankenship for their kindness.